<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[@janeeats on code and design]]></title>
  <link href="http://janeeats.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://janeeats.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-09T16:38:25-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://janeeats.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jane Vora]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Normalizing Data in Rails Forms for Beginners - Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://janeeats.github.com/blog/2013/03/09/normalizing-data-in-rails-forms-for-beginners-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-09T15:53:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://janeeats.github.com/blog/2013/03/09/normalizing-data-in-rails-forms-for-beginners-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post, part two of two, explains some customizations I included in a basic form for creating and editing groups on my team&#8217;s app, <a href="http://janeslunch.com">Jane&#8217;s Lunch</a>. In my previous post, part one, I explain how I <a href="http://janeeats.github.com/blog/2013/03/09/rails-form-helpers-for-beginners/">installed a timepicker</a> for the groups form. In this post, I explain how I created a custom form helper to normalize the states input for user addresses.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Jane&#8217;s Lunch is built on the <a href="https://hackfood.ordr.in/">Ordr.In API</a>, which requires the two-letter, state abbreviation for delivery addresses. To ensure that the data we received from the group form would be clean and play well with the Ordr.In API, I used a custom form helper that would normalize the states input for group addresses.</p>

<p>I put the following code in the group helper file:</p>

<pre><code>def us_states
[
  ['Alabama', 'AL'],
  ['Alaska', 'AK'],
  ['Arizona', 'AZ'],
  ['Arkansas', 'AR'],
  ['California', 'CA'],
  ['Colorado', 'CO'],
  ['Connecticut', 'CT'],
  ['Delaware', 'DE'],
  ['District of Columbia', 'DC'],
  ['Florida', 'FL'],
  ['Georgia', 'GA'],
  ['Hawaii', 'HI'],
  ['Idaho', 'ID'],
  ['Illinois', 'IL'],
  ['Indiana', 'IN'],
  ['Iowa', 'IA'],
  ['Kansas', 'KS'],
  ['Kentucky', 'KY'],
  ['Louisiana', 'LA'],
  ['Maine', 'ME'],
  ['Maryland', 'MD'],
  ['Massachusetts', 'MA'],
  ['Michigan', 'MI'],
  ['Minnesota', 'MN'],
  ['Mississippi', 'MS'],
  ['Missouri', 'MO'],
  ['Montana', 'MT'],
  ['Nebraska', 'NE'],
  ['Nevada', 'NV'],
  ['New Hampshire', 'NH'],
  ['New Jersey', 'NJ'],
  ['New Mexico', 'NM'],
  ['New York', 'NY'],
  ['North Carolina', 'NC'],
  ['North Dakota', 'ND'],
  ['Ohio', 'OH'],
  ['Oklahoma', 'OK'],
  ['Oregon', 'OR'],
  ['Pennsylvania', 'PA'],
  ['Puerto Rico', 'PR'],
  ['Rhode Island', 'RI'],
  ['South Carolina', 'SC'],
  ['South Dakota', 'SD'],
  ['Tennessee', 'TN'],
  ['Texas', 'TX'],
  ['Utah', 'UT'],
  ['Vermont', 'VT'],
  ['Virginia', 'VA'],
  ['Washington', 'WA'],
  ['West Virginia', 'WV'],
  ['Wisconsin', 'WI'],
  ['Wyoming', 'WY']
]
end
</code></pre>

<p>My group helper file is located in janeslunch/app/helpers/group_helper.rb.</p>

<p>Then in the view for the group form, I added this form helper to call the us_states helper:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;%= f.label(:state) %&gt;
&lt;%= f.select :state, us_states%&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>On the frontend, the states are spelled out in the input dropdown:
<img src="http://janeeats.github.com/images/states-form-helper-frontend.jpg" title="States Form Helper Input Dropdown" alt="Form Helper Example " /></p>

<p>In the database, the states data is saved in the format that the Ordr.in API likes:
<img src="http://janeeats.github.com/images/states-form-helper-db.png" title="States Form Helper Helps us Normalize Data Inputs in our DB" alt="Form Helper Example " /></p>

<p><strong>Resources</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Help from StackOver flow for my <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/6400010/rails-select-drop-down-for-states">states select tag</a></li>
<li>If you need select tags for other geographic locations, check out this handy gem <a href="https://github.com/jim/carmen">Carmen</a> (and for <a href="https://github.com/jim/carmen-rails">rails</a>).</li>
<li>Rails Guide for <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/form_helpers.html">Form Helpers</a></li>
<li>Listened to this <a href="https://soundcloud.com/charlotte-sky/sets/2013-remix">playlist</a> while writing this post.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Normalizing Data in Rails Forms for Beginners - Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://janeeats.github.com/blog/2013/03/09/rails-form-helpers-for-beginners/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-09T13:23:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://janeeats.github.com/blog/2013/03/09/rails-form-helpers-for-beginners</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My Flatiron School team, <a href="http://twitter.com/ACrystalC">Crystal</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/timspeaking">Tim</a> &amp; <a href="http://twitter.com/TylerMDavis">Tyler</a>, and I recently presented our group project, <a href="http://janeslunch.com">Jane&#8217;s Lunch</a>, at a <a href="http://www.meetup.com/nyc-on-rails/">NYC on Rails MeetUp</a>. Jane&#8217;s Lunch is a web application that makes lunch delivery for group orders easy and fun.</p>

<p>I worked on a small piece of our Groups controller and some of the basic forms for creating and editing groups. This post is part one of two. In part one, I explain how I installed a timepicker for the group forms. In part two, I explain how I created a custom form helper to normalize the states input for user addresses.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>TimePicker</h2>

<p>Our group form requires users to select a designated lunch time. We wanted to normalize the time data so that we wouldn&#8217;t have problems parsing different time formats (e.g. &#8220;1:30PM&#8221; vs. &#8220;1:30 p.m.&#8221; vs. &#8220;13:30&#8221;). A timepicker would solve this issue. I found <a href="http://jdewit.github.com/bootstrap-timepicker/">Bootstrap Timepicker</a>, a timepicker built by <a href="https://github.com/jdewit/bootstrap-timepicker">@jdewit</a> for use with Twitter Bootstrap.</p>

<p>To install the gem, I added this line to our Gemfile:</p>

<pre><code>gem 'bootstrap-timepicker-rails'
</code></pre>

<p>Next, I added this line to install the CSS for Bootstrap Timepicker:</p>

<pre><code> *= require bootstrap-timepicker
</code></pre>

<p>Then, I added this line to link to the JavaScript file for Bootstrap Timepicker:</p>

<pre><code>//= require bootstrap-timepicker
</code></pre>

<p>For beginners, you&#8217;ll want to include the entire line if you are installing the css and javascript. The code looks commented out, but Rails will actually implement that code even though it&#8217;s commented out.</p>

<p>In the view for our group form, I added the following:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;%= f.label(:lunch_time) %&gt;
  &lt;div class='input-append bootstrap-timepicker' style='display: inline;'&gt;
    &lt;input id='lunch_time' class='input-small' type='text' name='group[lunch_time]'&gt;
    &lt;span class='add-on'&gt;&lt;i class='icon-time'&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;
  $(document).ready(function(){
    $('#lunch_time').timepicker({
      template: 'dropdown',
      minuteStep: 15,
      showMeridian: false,
      showSeconds: false,
      defaultTime: '&lt;%= @group.lunch_time || "12:00" %&gt;'
    });
  });
  &lt;/script&gt; 
</code></pre>

<p>Here&#8217;s a breakdown to explain the block of code above:
<img src="http://janeeats.github.com/images/timepicker-step1.png" title="Bootstrap Timepicker Code Implementation Example" alt="Timepicker Code " />
Make sure to use an id not a class for the input selector that timepicker calls. I initially made lunch_time another class for the input instead of an id and it did not work.</p>

<p><img src="http://janeeats.github.com/images/timepicker-step2.png" title="Bootstrap Timepicker Code Implementation Example" alt="Timepicker Code " />
I was wary of using an input form helper, so I just used regular HTML and mixed it in with the erb format. However, I wanted to make sure that my input name would be passed along with the rest of the group data in the params hash, so I used my browser inspector to check the name format for other inputs that used the rails form helpers. The names were set to &#8216;group[attribute_name]&#8217; so that&#8217;s the format I followed for the timepicker input.</p>

<p><img src="http://janeeats.github.com/images/timepicker-step3.png" title="Bootstrap Timepicker Code Implementation Example" alt="Timepicker Code " />
My timepicker() call would not work without the document.ready.</p>

<p><img src="http://janeeats.github.com/images/timepicker-step4.png" title="Bootstrap Timepicker Code Implementation Example" alt="Timepicker Code " />
I set the configurations for timepicker based on the <a href="http://jdewit.github.com/bootstrap-timepicker/">documentation</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://janeeats.github.com/images/timepicker-step5.png" title="Bootstrap Timepicker Code Implementation Example" alt="Timepicker Code " />
The timepicker is a little buggy if you do not set a defaultTime. In some cases, the timepicker will show NaN:NaN if you don&#8217;t have any defaultTime set.</p>

<p>If the defaultTime, is only set to &#8220;12:00&#8221;, then the timepicker will always show &#8220;12:00,&#8221; even if the user has already set a lunch time.</p>

<p>The code fix above lets us set the timepicker to show the lunch time previously specified by the user or to show &#8220;12:00&#8221; if the user has not yet set it.</p>

<p><strong>Resources Links</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://jdewit.github.com/bootstrap-timepicker/">Bootstrap Timepicker</a>: A TimePicker built for use with Twitter Bootstrap</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tispratik/bootstrap-timepicker-rails">Gem</a> for integrating Bootstrap Timepicker with Rails asset pipeline</li>
<li>Rails Guide for <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/form_helpers.html">Form Helpers</a></li>
<li>I listened to this <a href="https://soundcloud.com/strangemachinemusic/sets/cool-2013">Playlist</a> while writing this blog post.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jane Dreams of Programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://janeeats.github.com/blog/2013/02/24/how-to-eat-an-elephant/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-24T14:33:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://janeeats.github.com/blog/2013/02/24/how-to-eat-an-elephant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>How Programming Is Changing The Way I View Everything</h2>

<p>Lately, I&#8217;ve been dreaming of programming. In my dreams, I&#8217;m breaking down problems, speaking of them in terms of coding metaphors. It reminds me of my dreams in Chinese while I studied abroad in Beijing my junion year of college. Living in China changed how I saw everything&#8230; for example I will never, ever take Modern Plumbing for granted again. I wanted to share two observations on how learning Ruby these 3 past weeks has already profoundly changed me.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>How Do You Eat an Elephant? One Bite at a Time.</strong>
I recently had a skype session with my business partner. We&#8217;ve been trying to launch a business for the past year or so. We&#8217;ve hit so many road blocks. Learning to program really highlighted for me the source of our problems. We were trying to bite off more than we could chew. Instead of trying to solve one problem at a time, we were trying to solve 20 simultaneously. It&#8217;s easier to start off simply and then build up into something more complex.</p>

<p><strong>Embrace the Frustration.</strong>
Programming is challenging, rewarding, and at time extremely frustrating. Being frustrated is part of the process. I&#8217;m not going to master everything in Ruby right away. I am learning to be comfortable with the idea that every line of code I&#8217;m testing will not pass on the first try. If programming was just that easy then wouldn&#8217;t be so rewarding learning it.</p>

<p><strong>Use Your Broken-Ass Skills Constantly To Become Fluent.</strong>
In the same way I learned Chinese by living and studying in Beijing, the Flatiron School is truly an immersive way to learn programming - just dive in and try to use the little code you know as often as possible. The language will start to feel more fluent the more you use it. I need to remind myself constantly that it&#8217;s ok to just use my broken ass Ruby and that eventually it will be come <a href="http://eloquentruby.com/">eloquent Ruby</a>&#8230; once I finish that book and put it into practice.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jiro Dreams of Sushi and Jane Dreams of Applications]]></title>
    <link href="http://janeeats.github.com/blog/2013/02/05/why-i-am-at-the-flatiron-school/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-05T17:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://janeeats.github.com/blog/2013/02/05/why-i-am-at-the-flatiron-school</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Why am I at the Flatiron School?</h2>

<p>While I liked my old job as the Interactive Designer/Developer for the New York City Economic Development Corporation, I was ready for a change. I&#8217;m pretty sure if I had to design just one more email template or tweak one more WordPress theme, I was gonna go crazy. I fell out of love with design at my old job. Then I encountered two pieces of inspiration that helped me find my way&#8230;</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>Jiro Dreams of Sushi.</strong> It&#8217;s on Netflix, so if you haven&#8217;t seen it yet, I highly recommend you watch it or at least add it to your <a href="http://movies.netflix.com/WiMovie/Jiro_Dreams_of_Sushi/70181716?locale=en-US" title="Jiro Dreams of Sushi on Netflix Streaming">instant queue</a>. In case you haven&#8217;t heard of it before, Jiro Dreams of Sushi is a documentary that follows Jiro, an 85-year-old master sushi chef in Japan and owner of Sukiyabashi Jiro, a Michelin three-star, 10-seat restaurant.</p>

<p>On the second time I watched it, I was really struck by the way Jiro spoke about his craft. He clearly loves his work and it drives him. He strives for perfection.</p>

<blockquote><p>Jiro says:
&#8220;Once you decide your profession, you must immerse yourself in the study of it. You must learn to fall in love with your work. Never complain about your work. You must dedicate your life to mastering that skill. That&#8217;s the secret of success&#8230; and is the key to being regarded honorably.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>As a web designer, I realized that I needed to immerse myself in the study of web development.</strong> I needed to figure out a way to fall back in love with web design. I knew that I couldn&#8217;t keep talking and dreaming about &#8220;wouldn&#8217;t it be cool if&#8230;&#8221; applications. I must build the applications I want to use.</p>

<blockquote><p>His oldest son, Yoshikazu, who leads the work at his father&#8217;s restaurant, says of his father:
&#8220;Always look ahead and above yourself. Always try to improve on yourself. Always strive to elevate your craft. That&#8217;s what he taught me.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>From a career perspective, I knew that in order to elevate my work, I needed to be able to provide more than simple front end design. With HTML/CSS skills being almost a requirement nowadays for most web designers, eventually I would have to learn how to program.</p>

<p><strong>I first heard about Ruby on Rails</strong> from my oldest brother, <a href="http://twitter.com/theevo" title="@theevo">Theo</a>, who is a huuuuge fan of <a href="http://37signals.com/" title="the coolest company">37signals</a> (for those who don&#8217;t know 37signals gave birth to Ruby on Rails). I had been curious about learning Ruby on Rails for some time and that&#8217;s what led me to find the <a href="http://flatironschool.com/" title="Learn Ruby on Rails in NYC">Flatiron School</a>.</p>

<p>Lastly, I want to end with a <strong>book recommendation: <em>Steal Like an Artist</em> by Austin Kleon.</strong> I think the tagline, &#8220;10 Things Nobody Told You About Being Creative,&#8221; sums it up well. I think a bit more accurate tagline is &#8220;10 Guidelines to Help You In Being Creative.&#8221; The book is an excellent read.. but if you&#8217;re on a tight budget, he&#8217;s got a great <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;v=oww7oB9rjgw" title="Austin Kleon TED Talk on Creative Work">TED talk</a>.</p>

<p><strong>To anyone out there stuck in a rut,</strong> Kleon&#8217;s book really inspired me to outline concrete actions to start producing creative work again. It literally motivated me to clean everything on, inside, and around my desk (both physical and virtual). It motivated me to make changes in the way I work to be more productive.</p>

<p>What have y&#8217;all found helpful for encouraging big life shifts?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
